Guide to the George Frederick Gundelfinger Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
George Frederick Gundelfinger papers
1891-1969
MS 693
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
16.92
(13 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, publications of The New Fraternity, and other books, pamphlets, and unpublished writings of George Frederick Gundelfinger who made a lifetime crusade of sending his publications and moral admonitions to Yale University. Yale's suit against him in 1939 for sending obscenity through the mail is documented by trial transcripts. Also in the papers are photographs, newspaper clippings, printed matter, and books on mathematics. There is also an edited diary describing a family tour of Europe in 1908.
Gundelfinger, George Frederick, 1883-1974
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of George Gundelfinger, 1973. Transfer from Hall of Graduate Studies, 2004. Gift of Elizabeth Gundelfinger, 2016.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers of George Frederick Gundelfinger contain correspondence, newspaper clippings, publications of The New Fraternity, and other books, pamphlets, and unpublished writings by Gundelfinger. The transcripts of his trial are also included, as are diplomas, sheet music for compositions by Gundelfinger, paintings by him, photographs, printing plates and layouts for publications, and writings by others, mostly on mathematics. The papers are completely unprocessed and disorganized, and contain numerous duplicates of many of the publications. There is also an addition which contains an edited diary describing a family tour of Europe in 1908.
The following pages contain a box list of the collection and a more detailed list of printed items in the papers; this list is not comprehensive.
These papers were donated to Yale University in 1973 by George Frederick Gundelfinger. Further correspondence and other papers can be found in the Yale Archives, RU 50.
Biographical / Historical
George Frederick Gundelfinger, a teacher of mathematics and a writer, was born in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, in 1884. He earned a B.S. from Sheffield Scientific School, Yale University in 1906 and a Ph.D. in math in 1909. He taught math at Yale from 1909 to 1913, and he also taught at the University of Pittsburgh and at Carnegie Institute of Technology. He wrote and printed the Interquadrangular, an independent Yale paper, and founded the brotherhood, "The New Fraternity." Upon retiring from teaching, Gundelfinger began a lifetime of moral crusading by sending his publications and admonitions to the students of Yale University.
Eccentrics and eccentricities; Mathematics; Obscenity (Law); Prisoners' writings; Gundelfinger, George Frederick, 1883-1974; Yale University -- History
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, writings, newspaper clippings (completely unsorted), [ca. 1906-1960s] (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, writings, newspaper clippings (completely unsorted), [ca. 1906-1960s] (Box 2)
  - Letters to officials, entitled "Back o' Bars", [1940s-1950s] (Box 2)
  - "Prison Penned Paragraphs", [1940s-1950s] (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets addressed to Judge Wallace S. Courley, [1950s] (Box 3)
  - Trial transcripts, [1940s] (Box 3)
  - Musical manuscripts, undated (Box 3)
  - Three scrapbooks of pamphlets and leaflets with printing costs, 1916-1927, 1928-1939, 1939-1966 (Box 4)
  - Daybook, 1944-1952 (Box 4)
  - Pamphlets and leaflets, [1940s-1960s] (Box 5)
  - Printing plates, undated (Box 6)
  - Printing plates and layouts, undated (Box 7)
  - Notebook with clippings, undated (Box 8)
  - Card files on mathematics, undated (Box 8)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 8)
  - Newspaper clippings, [1940s-1960s] (Box 8)
  - Books by G. F. Gundelfinger, 1911-1960 (Box 9)
  - Books by others, largely mathematical, 1891-1939 (Box 10)
  - Diplomas, photographs, paintings, printed matter, 1899-1952, undated (Folder 11)
- Additional Material, Accession 2005-M-024
  - Collage of sketches relating to The New Fraternity, [1939?] (Folder 1)
- Additional Material, 1908; Accession 2016-M-078
  - Doing Europe in 1908: Four Diaries in One, by Bertha C., Norma M., Hilda A., and George F. Gundelfinger, edited and illustrated by George F. Gundelfinger
    - Manuscript copy, bound, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Photocopy, bound, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- List of Printed Items in the George Frederick Gundelfinger Papers
  Scope and Contents
  (*) Number in parentheses relates to bibliography printed in The Storm of Protest, 1944.
  - Yale's New Fraternity versus Roman Catholic Fascism (63)*
  - Storm of Protest (85)*
  - Gundelfinger's reply to Gorokhoff's Question, 4 pp., 8.5 x 5.5"
  - The Interquadrangular - Yale's Ultimate Social System, 14 pp., 8.5 x 5.5"
  - Interquadrangular, volumes I-XVII
  - The New Fraternity: Yale's Anniversary 250th: (1916 Pub.), stamped, Emerson-Conduct of Life, Novel "New Frat." (5)*
  - The New Fraternity: Yale's Anniversary 250th, not stamped (5)*
  - The New Fraternity: Yale's Anniversary -Fly Leaves, stamped in black for page 263.
  - The New Fraternity: Parry Profile, Harkness Tower, place in book pages 262-263
  - Interquadrangular -three incomplete sets, numbers 1-225, (226-250?), 252-260.
  - Interquadrangular volumes 9-12
    - Interquadrangular number XVIISignatures 8.5 x 5.5" pp. 1025-1088
    - Interquadrangular XVI 8.5 x 5.5"pp. 789-804
    - Interquadrangular XVI signatures 8.5 x 5.5"pp. 789-804, 853-868, 885-900, 901-916
    - Interquadrangular (Cigam-start)485-756, 805-836
  - The New Fraternity, 1916, light blue cover and dust jacket (5)*
  - Ten Years at Yale (3)*
  - Essays of Elihu, 1923 (13)*
  - Three Books, 23 pp.
  - My Dismissal (12)*
  - Glimmerclass (47)*
  - The Man of the New Fraternity, reprint of Yale News - That Fellow Gundelfinger is to be reprinted on blank side from Yale News, 12 x 16", 1 sheet
  - Spooks on Parade (49)*
  - Lady Nic (60)*
  - To Have Loved and Lost (62)*
  - The Green Invasion (59)*
  - Cigam (45)*
  - Roosevelt Speedocity (50)*
  - War as a Means for Abolishing War, 4 pp., 8.5 x 5.5"
  - Jackson "Justice" at Nuerenberg, 4 pp., 5 x 8" (82?)*
  - James Rowland to the Dark Tower (66)*
  - The Blue Light (57)*
  - Yale's New Fraternity versus Roman Catholic Fascism (63)*
  - Ace
  - The Decay of Bulldogism, 16 pp., 8.5 x 5.5"
  - The Decay of Bulldogism, 4threprint, 16 pp., 8.5 x 5.5"
  - Grid Diamond Riot, pamphlet, 8.5 x 5.5"
  - Leader in Elegy (5)*
  - Frat Fate (38)*
  - Why I am Opposed to College Fraternities (24)*
  - Yale New Fraternity in Self-Defense, 11 pp., 8.5 x 5.5" (80)*
  - College -Student Drinking (22)*
  - Lest We Forget (16)*
  - Alcohol, Tobacco and Sex (20)*
  - The Freedom of Shes (26)*
  - Prince Albert's Velvet Tuxedo (7)*
  - Yale Critic "Humorist" says Yale News of Gundelfinger, 4 pp.
  - 1939 Yale -An Angel Plays the Lyre (44)*
  - Hadley and Public Opinion (21)*
  - An Original Interpretation of Sexual Phenomena (9)*
  - The Disrespect for Scholarship, The Decline of Teaching, The Failure to Educate (37)*
  - Jes Tulef (35)*
  - The Ghost at Oyster Bay (31)*
  - Inter-Q As a Column, 4 pp., 8.5 x 5.5"
  - A Needless (?) Introduction to Seymour's Yale (72)*
  - The Storm of Protest That Will Never Come (85)*
  - Concerning Yale's Next President (52)*
  - The "Oxford-Cambridge" of America (34)*
  - Crucifixion by Surgery (74)*
  - Why the Freshman (67)*
  - The End of an Era, 7 pp. 8.5 x 5.5"
  - Graduate Degeneration - Alumni "Renascent" (34)*
  - Yale's Ultimate Social System (28)*
  - Vaterland and Alma Mater, 17 pp., 8.5 x 5.5"
  - "A" As an Art, pamphlet, 8.5 x 5.5"
  - End of Era, flier, 1 p., 10 x 15.5"
  - The Great Reliever (42)*
  - The Decay of Bulldogism (29)*
  - Yale's New Fraternity versus Roman Catholic Fascism (63)*
  - Ten Years at Yale (3)*
  - Wonderful Glorious Spring, sheet music
  - I Think of You, sheet music
  - Adventures of Jack, sheet music
  - Lonely, sheet music
  - All the World is in Love, sheet music
  - When Jerry Plays the Flute, sheet music
  - I Love to be Loved by a Baby, sheet music
  - Etching and Half Tones
  - GFG Theatric, 152 pp.